<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><xml>
   Hi, Felix. 

   Hi, Elisa. 

   Yeah. So we have started recording. 

   We are redoing portions of our discussion 

   on minimal computing, this time to 

   record them and hopefully be able to 

   work with them. So I think I'm scrolling 

   through here. Oh, and you have, I see, 

   already fleshed out your introduction. 

   You like that portion, because I was going 

   to start by saying, Felix, tell us 

   about your background with minimal computing, 

   but I think you've already got that. 

   Yes. 

   Where should we begin? 

   Do you want to talk about 

   your experiences in Nigeria? 

   with minimal, and how that has influenced 

   your perspective on our discussions 

   of minimal computing generally. Is 

   that a good starting point? Because 

   you had a lot to say, and it was very, 

   it was very important, I think, 

   for this piece to have that. 

   I guess that's a big question. 

   I think I would like to begin with the fact 

   that the concept of the term minimum 

   computing, was it a thing, was not a thing. 

   If I should talk retrospectively 

   from 2017 to 2021, 

   so maybe what would be the term would 

   be lack of funding lack of resources, 

   lack of infrastructure, what do we do? 

   So I think the drive sincerely back 

   then was to get people to know about DH. 

   The drive wasn't really that much about 

   projects. The drive was all about human capacity 

   development it's obvious not in humanities 

   alone across sciences and other disciplines 

   i'll take a quick example from sciences where 

   a phd student in biochemistry or any of the 

   sciences would like to run a lab session 

   for a dissertation she or she would need a 

   chemical and most likely they buy it from the 

   west it takes a long time to ship it down if 

   that person is unfortunate to have a pei we 

   don't call it pei a supervisor who holds a 

   lab who has funding who can buy the chemicals 

   otherwise they will have to be in rotation 

   until one finishes before the other can come 

   up so the humanity case is not out of point 

   it's a general norm so but the challenge 

   there would be we don't know can somebody teach 

   us to know have an idea so i think that was 

   pretty much that was the background of ddh 

   in nigeria from my own perspective the training 

   purposes let's get them trained let's 

   harm them the second shift which i really think 

   it's very important to talk about beyond 

   the human capacity development is to train 

   people to be able to use dh method in their 

   respective i will call it traditional research 

   you know it's a long journey now 

   to begin to talk about dh projects 

   which humanity um minimal 

   computing now becomes very a very 

   table tool i mean in terms of um 

   how do we do the project this is 

   not a question the question is we 

   don't really know about dh We want to 

   know about it. Now that you know, 

   let's lay our hands on a tiny research 

   within your own research and make a 

   paper publication and try Voyant or try 

   Hong Kong and see if you can tweak it 

   with African-American, Nigerian texts, 

   Nigerian literature, and see what happens 

   in Chinua Achebe's teens fall apart and see 

   how you can track places. that kind of thing 

   so that was that was rigorous i really 

   really want to point that out the the payoff 

   for the human capacity development really 

   really was a great deal so we started off from 

   the scratch um knowing about it and we scale 

   up from that i i could remember vividly 

   2021 um Professor Tunde, who happens to be 

   the Center for Digital Humanities in Lagos, 

   was able to bring people from not 

   only West Africa, I think West African 

   and East Africa early career 

   researchers to be trained. Of course, 

   thanks to the Volkswagen Foundation or the 

   German Foundation who always assist in training 

   and bringing people together. and many 

   from different disciplines from french from 

   english from humanities specific disciplines 

   came on board very excited to learn very happy 

   to see wow these two can do this one this 

   can turn my research around and within the 

   space of i mean a couple of couple of months 

   or let's say within that season what we 

   noticed of course i am a product of that noticeable 

   trend many got to western universities 

   to pursue that knowledge knowledge drive yeah 

   yeah so that was it picked you up and moved 

   you to new places and that also helps you 

   find new methods and new methods so it feels 

   like yeah we can't talk about minimal competing 

   in the global south without discussing 

   the importance of educating communities first 

   correct i i you you you have the right word 

   it's the community the community of practice 

   and you know what i'm pretty much sure 

   maybe from your background in the north that 

   might be similar there is this apathy against 

   learning or applying dh or dh2 or method to 

   our already registered long term over the 

   decade traditional research so the brevity of 

   to share, even when faculty members 

   don't like what he was doing. 

   Yeah, they don't want it. He is 

   a professor of digital studies, 

   where you call it discourse analysis. 

   And he works with political discourse of a 

   particular election year in 1993, which was 

   very, very funny. so he was able to produce 

   volumes and research in that area but when he 

   but when he traveled for his um um alexander 

   von um experience researcher fellowship 

   back then in germany he was introduced to the 

   edge so he came back he felt this is what is 

   going to happen now i have to train people 

   So he became the first person to be 

   called a professor in DH because he 

   brought everything down from Germany and 

   he brought trainer, coordinator, people 

   who can actually assist him. He brought 

   them down. And he also learned with 

   us, with the team and the community. 

   He learned together. He was able to 

   bring his expertise on board because 

   of his connections, to bring people 

   to come and train. Like I mentioned 

   last week, Alex was down in Lagos. 

   Ovin was in Lagos. 

   Dan and Old owner was in Lagos. 

   I mean, in person, 

   Queen did that remotely. 

   So a lot of people would 

   want to come down to teach. 

   That was the drive, and that was really 

   impactful. what we see um the trend we see 

   afterwards um was one two three four five number 

   keeps going on who went after beyond the 

   conferences and summer schools because he runs 

   summer schools and winter schools and 

   conferences then established through the training 

   established association like um like the 

   acm we have here uh digital humanity association 

   of nigeria and that was the first no 

   we don't we never had anyone that was the 

   first in the training so so what year was that 

   about just to put a pin on that and do you 

   know do you remember what year that was when 

   he had that first training 2017 yeah so 

   that's yes we had summer school we had conferences 

   uh 2018 the boss who again gave another 

   fund we have summer school 2019 till 2021 

   the 2021 was a combination of win either 

   winter school plus conference so we can wait 

   so it was busy with writing proposal for grants 

   i need help people need this people need 

   to and and the interesting part of it is 

   beyond the training like i mentioned we now 

   have an association of th um i think they run 

   i'm not pretty much sure if they run a 

   journal but the association was established and 

   the the migration of people to go to the 

   west to learn more was was really really um 

   interesting and from there we have postdocs 

   going into germany too through his own manpower 

   through his own connections through his 

   own training and these product students were 

   not the age inclined before they had a taste 

   of a summer school of a conference and they 

   just see oh this is what i'm doing i'm 

   being multimode at this course analysis i can 

   use it too okay and it became a postdoctoral 

   um training for them outside the country. 

   And to say the least, now we have a 

   subdiscipline branching out from there, which 

   is called corpus linguistics. They also 

   felt if Professor Tunde could take this 

   responsibility to train people, and they've 

   been doing some smaller data analysis, 

   this set of researchers, but they felt we 

   need a broad scale corpus. And they just 

   developed um that subdisciplines um from the 

   west um discipline of course linguistics so i 

   really really want to point that out i never 

   i wasn't sure i knew what of course um 

   when general came we heard about minimal 

   computing but do we really understand what minimal 

   computing is do we have cooperative 

   projects that we can sit down together like in 

   the west you have to work with other partners 

   do we have community partners that we want 

   to work together um to work on a project 

   and begin to think about what do we have 

   what approach we take we we don't have that 

   what do we need right what do we need and like 

   even what we would be willing to give up 

   you're just getting started so that last 

   question is sort of wait it's really maybe the 

   emphasis is on what do we need and what do 

   we have what do we have yeah so the the 

   approach to the questions will be different 

   from one global south country to another um 

   and i'm pretty much sure that's a good 

   consideration for us to talk about to really see 

   um the differences in approach even up even 

   when we in times conceptualize the minimum 

   computing in the global south we still have 

   to understand the background the cultural 

   differences and how that fits into the global 

   south i think that's a go start for me i 

   feel like listening to you describe this um 

   kind of the the origins of um digital 

   humanities um from what all the in in nigeria 

   and like sort of east africa right um west 

   africa yeah okay um the hearing you talk about 

   that because it was multiple countries and 

   many different people involved, but there's 

   this organizing effort and all of those. 

   One of the questions that might be directly 

   relevant to minimal computing in the 

   global South is what do we need to learn? 

   Because the decision that your mentor had 

   to make, you know the decisions that everyone 

   made in that moment were oh ant conch 

   is helpful to us or voyant is helpful as 

   a starting point and i remember making a 

   similar decision it's not related to your 

   situation but when new students are coming 

   to to learn what is digital humanities as 

   undergraduates even where i am i want them 

   to see oh a computer can look at text as 

   a bunch of little pieces and assemble them 

   and ant conch is my favorite i like voyant 

   too because it's pretty and it's easy 

   to use but ant conch is such a nice little 

   self-contained system and it's small and 

   you can learn how to customize it you can 

   learn how to customize both of those things 

   and i also liked working with them 

   together um to say look they work very 

   differently and you might want to 

   make a decision about which one of 

   these is better for what you're doing 

   and like right there we sort of shook hands 

   on a particular method i don't use voyant and 

   ant conch very much in my own professional 

   research but i like it as a starting point 

   to show people oh here's something interesting 

   you can do with computers and humanities 

   research questions so yeah and the linguistic 

   side of it is so important yeah i think 

   that's that's very important when we talk about 

   dh method in this method used in global stuff 

   i think it's very important to point to 

   that fact that if you want to train people the 

   community of practice the first thing would 

   be what do we train them um and what how 

   long can we go for them to really accumulate 

   and being able to use them so i remember um 

   priestly from canada also came to train us on 

   um buoyant and i think pretty much he brought 

   the book by rockwin and sinclair a 

   physical copy we should cite that in the paper 

   physical copy yeah physical books so 

   do you think why was that so 

   remarkable that it was a physical copy 

   and not just like a link that you would 

   look at it's I mean it's amazing 

   that we do physical books in digital 

   humanities I guess yeah like okay so 

   I remember before I could say I had that 

   much of the feeling was when I moved to 

   Loyola that my center has a copy. Then I 

   could grab it. I could read it. You know, 

   we talked about that last week. When you 

   talked about visiting the archives, Zit and 

   Lagos, I don't remember, but the physical 

   presence of resources, you couldn't take 

   that for granted. But if it was there, 

   being able to give somebody a book or share 

   it with somebody made a personal connection 

   with them or made it possible for you 

   to access an archive that you had to know 

   the humans involved. But like, do you 

   feel like that's also part of the digital 

   humanities training experience is there's 

   something reliable about having physical 

   resources that support your digital work? 

   I'm thinking about that in two ways. First 

   is the challenge of having access to resources 

   would be a major one. So when you now 

   see an example, you want to have that kind 

   of connection with the resources, either 

   manuscripts or textbook, and you would like to 

   continue to use them in such a way that you 

   know you don't have access to read again. 

   So I think the first thing 

   is the question of access. 

   Access. Access to funding, 

   access to resources, 

   access to textbook, 

   access to manuscript. It's a major challenge. 

   I remember when we were trained, at that 

   time, we were asked to check up Project 

   Gutenberg for copies of electronic books that 

   we can download. Because I remember AntCon 

   allows .txt files, so we have to convert the 

   PDF to .txt. That's part of the training. 

   Yeah, you have to learn document conversion. 

   Yeah. 

   But now we have the physical copy. So I 

   think that's very important. the second thing 

   that beyond access is um this kind of 

   sustained interest it gives you kind of sustained 

   interest when you have access to the 

   physical resources like the manuscripts in the 

   archives beyond the proposal beyond the 

   the the hamchair thinking about you want to 

   work on the research in the archive when 

   you have a touch with the physical material 

   the materiality gives you that kind of 

   sustained interest in that research it keeps you 

   awake helps you to think about it the the 

   archives of care if they they are fragile 

   the archive is or the material um material 

   effect is this so um i think the first thing 

   is the access the second one is the 

   sustained interest that the researcher get close 

   um get when they get close to to the 

   material object so it's it It kind of shapes 

   the paradigm of the traditional discipline. 

   When we read books, we do everything, 

   but this time around, you have a resource 

   to go back to like the human ethical 

   book. When you have issues with 

   and you have a book by your side, you 

   can flip through the pages and use it. 

   And I think, 

   I must say this, when rupico produced the um 

   edited digital black atlantic um professor 

   tunde um wrote a chapter and another scholar 

   from canada wrote another chapter i was in 

   nigeria i spoke with my brother in the u.s 

   paid for a physical copy i needed a physical 

   copy so when i moved in in january that was 

   my first welcome book i'm trying to see if i 

   have my physical copy here but i got a physical 

   copy of it too it might be in my office 

   school mine is in a chef with me here so when 

   i visited here it is oh cool physical book 

   yeah i want to read books like this in a 

   physical form yeah even though i don't know if 

   it's hard to get a digital copy but that's 

   just it you don't know if a digital copy is 

   available for free now it might be behind a 

   paywall i don't remember the situation with 

   this book but you know it's yeah i have this 

   book right someday it may be updated and 

   that's fine but i have the first one i mean just 

   to portray the fact of the fact of access 

   and the sustained interest i remember paying 

   in in of course conversion rate in nigeria 

   currency for my brother to keep to 

   to ship it to my brother's house in 

   the u.s and keep it for me when i came 

   i grab it this is my physical copy 

   it was like my introduction to 

   masters in dh in the u.s i have 

   that physical copy so when you see 

   when you see that you want to continue 

   in that path of the district where 

   you have access to resources which 

   is a challenge in the global stuff 

   access to resources access to manpower 

   access to manuscript it's a challenge even 

   when you think you have the limited access to 

   internet the wi-fi it's still a challenge 

   or limited limited access i remember was saying 

   this last week to the the power the power 

   source you don't have it all day so it's 

   still a challenge so imagine you want to run 

   some algorithm on your system and you have to 

   leave it so you have to look for whether 

   it's power source that can sustain your work 

   need electricity yeah and that's not granted 

   yeah oh it's it's a lot it's a lot because 

   we've learned to take up the challenge one 

   after the other I mean a little by little of 

   course minimally and to also see other resources 

   beyond the global south to ask for 

   resources beyond the global south I remember 2019 

   after the trainings we've had from Lagos 

   Professor Tunde was a chair within the Adho 

   2019 conference that specializes in training 

   african dh so i remember saying he sent it to 

   me and other people who had showed up during 

   some of the summer schools and conferences 

   you guys should apply he didn't tell us it 

   was part of the committee he just told us to 

   apply and we did and i think six of us or 

   if not less than six traveled to to the 

   netherlands to get a whole one week pre-conference 

   workshop so we had one week in lighting 

   2019 before we moved down to utrecht and the 

   training we got in in a week we're able to 

   produce a poster for the 2019 dh conference um 

   poster session which was just within one 

   week so it's great that he did not bring um 

   trained people brought people to come and train 

   us he also took us out to go and experience 

   the professional connections the professional 

   network i remember i met jeffrey walkway 

   in person you know you've read a book you 

   saw him you know that conference was over a 

   thousand or so participants so it's very 

   difficult to really grab people i remember working 

   with him and asking him questions you know 

   very implicitly about this amenity code is 

   going on and on and on so i could see that 

   kind of um his way of connecting us with the 

   professional world beyond the global south 

   practice or struggling or lack of this or 

   that so he was able to ship us out you go have 

   experience to really see how dh work outside 

   so that's that's immensely um important 

   for me to stress so it was instrumental yeah 

   it It sounds like bringing people from West 

   Africa to the Netherlands wasn't just about, 

   you know, you're going to learn these tools 

   and methods, but it feels to me, and just 

   from my own experience of being at DH 

   conferences and workshops, that you have an 

   opportunity to have a conversation with the 

   makers of that tool. And that if I know 

   Jeffrey Rockwell, I bet he started thinking 

   about some of your questions and said, oh, 

   you know, wait, maybe we should change 

   the tool a certain way or maybe we can, you 

   know, like we have a new challenge to 

   address with analyzing texts thanks to what 

   you're bringing. You are very, very right, 

   because we were trained on the pedagogical 

   landscape. We're trained to learn 

   how DH works in terms of practice. And I 

   took up that challenge because I was teaching 

   in an undergrad four -year college. So 

   I took up that challenge to also train. 

   I became not just a participant in some 

   of the summer schools and I became 

   a coordinator or taking a session because 

   we can't keep the pace of hiring 

   people from outside again. So the first 

   two, three sessions were to train us. 

   So some of us took up the challenge to 

   train. So I became very invested in training, 

   buoyant and conch. So I just have to study 

   it. Then I can replicate it with people. 

   And that becomes my way of reformalizing 

   some of the systems that were built 

   for the North or for the Western world, 

   which might not be correctly amenable 

   to our own practice in the global 

   south. So I have those kind of questions, 

   especially formal questions about 

   how it might not be appropriate to 

   work with our own local languages. 

   If it's OK, how do we tweak it to be 

   able to work with a multilingual setting? 

   Because sometimes when we use sentences 

   in Nigeria, for instance, in English 

   sentences, it's always embedded in our 

   cultural practices. so you have to you have 

   to ask again felix so what do you say 

   in the last sentence because i might be 

   hoovering from my culture and you know but 

   i'm still expressing this in english so when 

   we now begin to harvest some of the um post 

   post um civil post -independence literature 

   or pre-independence literature in nigeria 

   before 1960 you might be shocked that the ant 

   song of voyant will bring great patterns 

   out but you have to understand the um the 

   embedded culture within those constructions um 

   so it's beyond just bringing out patterns 

   you have to not see how like the current llms 

   what event is would help us to understand 

   the context beyond um regular expressions or 

   keyword search the keyword search may be very 

   great the keyword in context in we aren't 

   in ant conk is very great like some words 

   before and some what after by seafield there 

   is this disconnect for from the real culture 

   of of practice which brings out the text 

   so it's just way way way way different but 

   actually making me it's making me think i wonder 

   is ant conk more useful than you know 

   like taking a large language model now for 

   studying like kind of multilingual context 

   because it doesn't make assumptions. It just 

   breaks up particles the way you say to do it. 

   And then you see, yeah, I have that hunch, 

   but I never, you know, because I don't 

   work in such a rich multilingual context as 

   you. Yeah. That affirms something I 

   wondered because I enjoy showing my students 

   what AntConc can do. And I like that it 

   seems simple. I know it isn't, but it's 

   certainly simpler than a large language model 

   where we don't have as much opportunity 

   to adjust the way it's working, right? It 

   gets like, ooh, the smaller tool matters. 

   Yeah. And I think you're right. We don't 

   have access to the black box. We don't have 

   access to the upper parameters tuning. We 

   don't have access to the training data behind 

   it. We don't have access to the power 

   compute imagine do we have hpc in africa uh 

   human um high performing computing that can 

   handle such yeah i don't know and then do 

   we need it you know do we need it and it's 

   like maybe the minimal computing contacts 

   are kind of getting us to shout wait we're 

   doing perfectly we're doing better over here 

   with these tools that we can we can do 

   use ourselves yeah Yeah. We really need it. 

   Ant Pug's getting a wonderful shout out. 

   And so is Boyan. Those 

   tools are good. Yeah. 

   So now my takeaway is if I have to not sit 

   within the concept of digital humanities 

   project in Nigeria, maybe I want to 

   collaborate. I want to sit on the board. I want 

   to come to understand how people walk. 

   I'll be the one shouting, do we need it? Do 

   we need it? Do we need it? And that is, of 

   course, a minimal competing question. yeah 

   what do we have what do we have don't tell 

   me because i'm in the west i should i should 

   ask i should stamp every request what do we 

   have i might be in the west but we are back 

   at home what do we have do we have um 

   spreadsheets can we use um collection builder 

   who with jekyll or can we use omeka sites to 

   just bring out those um instances of each 

   page or we use um wakutu if those are horror 

   history or collections from the community 

   what do we have and i think back to the question 

   of what do we teach which might be part 

   of what minima principles can be expanded 

   to in the global south what do we teach we 

   also consider open access to um to the tools 

   so that's why we went after aunt kong and 

   when i because they were free access you know 

   that kind of thing so it's very important 

   um in doing the h in the global south either 

   in practice or in training or in teaching 

   we also consider what we teach um because we 

   want to teach um tools that method that 

   people can use after the training without calling 

   you again without asking you for technical 

   help and without paying i remember professor 

   tunde was beforehand from general training 

   was using sketch engine which is not free 

   i mean you can you can see you can enjoy 

   the free features but when you want to do 

   real work you have to do so if he has one of 

   those tools where you have to you start to 

   realize its limits after a while yeah after 

   a while so if he has the bandwidth to pay um 

   at his own crater the the community he 

   brought together don't have the money to pay for 

   speech engine so we have to now streamline 

   who is coming to train us on the basis of 

   the open source software so what do we teach 

   is going to be and a good important principle 

   to add to the global south minimal 

   computing what do you teach and i had i had two 

   ideas here that like what do we teach is a 

   new question to add and also what what do we 

   need to change about our tools right because 

   right because that conversation as you 

   begin to use the tools in your own context that 

   are different from the way they were 

   originally written um the digital humanities 

   tools change maybe become more efficient maybe 

   handle a greater complexity of or you know 

   more use cases as you introduce them yeah 

   yeah i think it's a good question to really 

   think about um um what do we teach and what 

   do we change in the existing existing and i 

   think the goal will be for tools that are um 

   quite working well with um existing research 

   paradigms in the humanities in global south 

   that would be a good way to start um see 

   what you can do which is before you begin to 

   know the limitation that this tool doesn't 

   offer you. So the next stage will not be to 

   see what we have in terms of manpower. A CS 

   professor, an English professor might need 

   to come together having understood how buoyant 

   can work, but with the limitation of 

   multilingual setting or multilingual languages, 

   they might need to come together with a 

   simple page or whatever tool that would help 

   them to understand. So that commitment also is 

   very key. They can build up some little 

   structure or systems that will help them to 

   now understand their language and help people 

   to do research within that circle. So if we 

   graduate progressively from what do we teach 

   and what do we have to what tools do we 

   change, we could actually gain the manpower or 

   the expertise to be able to think critically 

   about software studies, critical understanding 

   of softwares and how those softwares 

   work. And we are not really keen about the 

   limitations. We just wanted to do something 

   for us. But I think after a while, we might 

   begin to think about what are the limitations 

   based on existing research we have used it 

   to carry out in our own personal research. 

   And the question we are asking now in 

   this research are not answered, what 

   tool do we need to change or features? 

   Before Consuelo jumps in, I 

   remember just an anecdote. 

   I was a fan, still in the same 

   space of minimal computing, 

   but not called minimal computing. 

   I was a fan of the reference 

   software management Mendeley, 

   which is different from Sotero in the West, 

   it's different from um um endnote a paid 

   version of the rest i did that successfully 

   training university students from school to 

   school because it it was free i still free 

   and and lcvia acquired it i remember the 

   question of what to do we need to change i went 

   during the 2019 conference workshop I went 

   to Elsevier headquarters I left my oh my 

   goodness you went and bearded the tech giants 

   in their lair oh my god this is wonderful 

   okay and I asked them we need to make changes 

   in the tour I went with from Nigeria with 

   a proposal I am the one training and this 

   is what we found out can you at me uh-huh 

   can you make these changes for africa did they 

   do it i sat with the tech people you know 

   it was like a costly talk um walk walking 

   you know my host was able to take me through 

   the different sections of the tech tech and 

   i was serious like i need help all the way 

   from africa i was of course before that i 

   was an ambassador for mentally because i 

   trained so they support everything i do with 

   shipment for merchandise even when i go to 

   loyola we still have this is shipped something 

   back to loyola for me because loyola i mean 

   the west don't really do mendeley like 

   that so i couldn't sustain that in the west i 

   have to write a mail i said um i mean the 

   west now i'm not thinking mendeley will be 

   the thing it's zotero so yeah zotero is the 

   one i but i think once a group of people 

   invests heavily in a bibliography resource 

   software and then it does not meet your needs. 

   There's a great pain to that. 

   And the pain of transition is something 

   that people really get upset about. 

   Do you feel as if your trip to speak 

   to Elsevier, did they make any changes 

   or were they sort of not listening 

   in the same way that like Jeffrey 

   Rockwell would for making a change. 

   My proposal was accepted, but 

   was kept in the pipeline. They 

   had other features to roll out. 

   So mine would be a long time coming. So 

   they had other features to roll out from 

   the tech team, and they have to prioritize 

   those features before attending to my 

   proposal. That was 2019. And maybe Elsevier 

   is too big. And so from the context of 

   minimal computing, that like industrial, 

   like, that's an interesting perspective 

   on minimalism that I don't know 

   that we talk about very much. But like 

   your decision to work with a tool now 

   might be different now that you've 

   had that experience, right? Correct. 

   Yeah. 

   Yeah. 

   The way software is made. 

   So Consuela, let's sum 

   up a little bit here. 

   Felix has been on fire. I've just been asking 

   him little questions. But we came up with 

   a couple of questions to add to the the 

   minimal computing, the standard minimal 

   computing list, which is minimal computing in 

   the global south, like helps us expand those 

   questions to what do we need to learn? And 

   what do we learn and teach? What do we need 

   to learn and teach? And what do we need to 

   change about our tech? And like those two 

   things, like that's what Felix has been going 

   on about. it's like well i i went to to 

   talk to these people and you've had a couple 

   of different stories about that where going 

   to the netherlands and talking to some dh 

   developers of voyant lets you realize oh 

   these people are approachable and now they're 

   really interested and now this is like a 

   scholarly product to you know keep applying 

   and changing the little things like voyant 

   and anconc right like those things you can 

   talk to the developers and when a tool is 

   like run by else severe you realize it's very 

   different to talk to those people yeah so 

   but then you start to have as you use the 

   tools in the global south and as people are 

   learning they start to recognize we need to 

   make changes so that this works with the 

   resources we have and what we need to do so 

   i guess that's i think the summary that 

   was a lot better than the ai summary 

   we started this conversation like hating the 

   ai summary because it actually made it 

   really hard to revise anything you know because 

   it sounds so authoritative and it's so 

   general and it lost all the little glimmering 

   details and it was just ah i know i was just 

   like saying like first thing the only help 

   you have is a chatbot which i probably hate 

   it uh because it never gives you the answer 

   it's like oh i can answer that but you will 

   ask me this and it's like nope i need you 

   to tell us what we said it is where it is 

   my transcription where it is my record still 

   still saying the same like oh it could take 

   days to be ready and it's like nope no no 

   just lost it somewhere it's somewhere in some 

   cloud maybe Felix do you remember hearing 

   the little voice saying recording in progress 

   because I don't know like yeah yes even 

   on my screen so it did get recorded yes yes 

   Because I asked you, did you hear it? And 

   Felix looked at me and said, yes, I hear it. 

   And I was like, okay. Okay, 

   so that wasn't just me. 

   I had the recording thing, because there 

   was two signs. It's the recording sign, 

   and it's the sign of the AI working. 

   And I have both of them on. 

   It's on now. I mean, it's also on right now. 

   The recording in progress is on. I don't 

   have the AI companion on because I hate it. 

   I actually wonder if the AI companion itself 

   interfered with accessing the recording. 

   This is a whole minimal competing 

   question, isn't it? Yeah. We are 

   relying on Zoom to provide a service, 

   and it is concealing things from us. 

   Yes. 

   I must say the only thing that I really 

   like, I didn't try it now, but it 

   has the possibility of translating 

   the notes. I didn't check how good they 

   were translated to other languages, 

   which is something interesting with AI. 

   It will help sometimes the miscommunications 

   that happen with multilingual culture 

   backgrounds. yeah felix was talking about that 

   too which we'll see like multilingual text 

   analysis when the conversation is meant 

   to have two languages in it is tough for ai 

   sometimes yeah yeah so yeah i i don't know 

   it's so i try to like get as much as 

   information i was able i was like give me like 

   points when like what people said don't give 

   me like a general idea that's that's when 

   i uh the like then like elisa said and felix 

   said and like i can assume our use points 

   exactly this could guide us throughout the 

   discussion kind of we we and and i suppose we 

   have a question of like you know how much 

   of this document that i'm looking at over on 

   the screen will we want to use because we're 

   about to get the transcript dump like in the 

   format that i showed you and like you know 

   we can remove all the time stamps and stuff 

   instead of move things into place so there's 

   going to be another layer of complexity but 

   I think having our own words is is going to 

   be important wherever we can sort of patch 

   them in and move things around I tried 

   reorganizing some things like Consuelo when you 

   had written a lot I tried to move some things 

   together to where they sort of seemed like 

   they were part of our conversation last week 

   so I guess I'm kind of looking to see 

   we needed a lot from Felix and a lot 

   of what you just said and Felix is 

   like so much more developed than what 

   you said last week. So I think it's 

   good we came back and did this anyway. 

   What do you think, I mean, part of the issue 

   here is like for a little while it was just 

   sort of me and Felix going back and forth. 

   So we might sort of artificially patch 

   Consuelo in, but is there a piece of this 

   where we should pick up and continue, 

   like from the document? 

   What do we have? What do we need? 

   I guess part of what we just did was reframe 

   the questions a little bit, add two new 

   questions. That's a substantial, big change. 

   Felix was tossing out source citations that 

   we need to put in. One of them was Jeffrey 

   Rockwell's book on, well, Jeffrey Rockwell 

   et al. on, was it Voyance? And the idea of 

   having physical books as resources and material 

   stuff was important. the hermeneutica 

   yes um yeah i think we have to add also um we 

   discussed this uh last week the other 

   question about like for whom we're making the 

   project okay and we talk about that i think 

   it's it's in here actually it's when i was 

   was it captured i mentioned at the beginning 

   of my introduction kind of okay was that 

   captured or we should or you can read was it 

   captured in the summary or we should just 

   yes i think it is in some ways it's not it's 

   good enough because yeah we're realizing like 

   it lost examples and details yes and 

   there's no bridge in the end of this i know um 

   yeah i let me see it does have a bridge but 

   it's not as good as our bridge yeah i i think 

   this was like balancing technical uh skills 

   and culture this is when felix started 

   talking about like the work in the archive 

   uh the work with the materials uh in nigeria 

   that the person is creating this archive and 

   going into and doing this by memory and 

   going into the community and build all the 

   materials with the community and we were talking 

   about all these things are like around 

   a digital printer necessarily and then uh 

   yeah like projects in multilingual environments 

   and we talked about the yeah like lack of 

   electricity and stuff too that yeah yeah 

   so it is on the balancing technical skills 

   and culture kind of point in the document um 

   so yeah it was like we were like how we 

   there's like different things like like 

   skills like i can't remember i say like 

   we if we have like we can have a project 

   with the best programmer server but 

   and the best technology but if we made 

   the whole project and it's not available 

   right availability yeah it happened with the 

   bamboo project when they were like doing an 

   archive for it was it was for a Caribbean 

   island it's Puerto Rico or something or Dominica 

   and I'm trying to remember they came to 

   do a talk in a class on that and they made 

   all this archive and when they get there their 

   internet weren't able to download or to 

   show the images so it was basically only to 

   show off outside the community that it was 

   meant for I think it was bamboo that had that 

   problem i cannot remember very well um when 

   we when you were discussing the rss feed and 

   how you came to um kind of appreciate that 

   i wonder if you want to say a little bit more 

   about like why that was so helpful in the 

   context of podcasting because like that's a 

   very yeah yeah yeah uh okay let's well so so 

   actually like and having just been listening 

   to felix like he was talking about like 

   the importance of getting people together 

   educating them and then like bringing people into 

   contact with each other like felix your 

   context was kind of physically moving people 

   physically accessing books like ripsy's digital 

   black atlantic which we both realized we 

   have physical copies of that we're really 

   happy that we have because that's a matter of 

   access so you're not sure if the digital is 

   going to be available if you have a book you 

   can share it with another human being in 

   your physical presence but like what we do 

   with digital things um when we're trying to 

   make them accessible when we don't have we can't 

   be sure from year to year if it's going 

   to be available things like rss feeds really 

   matter yes yeah right yeah they are amazing 

   i feel like i always like go crazy on 

   the rss well i mean it's just coming 

   back to that kids just to get it back 

   down in the recording yeah yeah podcasting 

   and audio it's like the career that 

   i don't have that i dream like my 

   sustain like my nine to five kind of um 

   no i think uh rsss are are amazing and it's 

   a great example of a minimal computing 

   tool in a way that they are very conscious 

   on the user point of view like when you're 

   making a project using errors files 

   there are there can be shared on um software 

   like a catcher like we call it a podcast 

   catcher audio catcher you can hear in there 

   you can put it like on your website uh 

   it's very easy doesn't need like high internet 

   it was made in the 90s so it's thank you 

   for very very slow equipment and even in 

   case that you don't have anything like digital 

   like like a hardware to hear it you could 

   use radio if you're at those sources so i 

   know a couple of cases on um there is like the 

   first podcast that and i talk about this 

   and another chapter of another book but there 

   is this first podcast it's a mexican one 

   actually and it's from the 90s it's like even 

   early that the first thing we call podcast 

   but it's not on like history books because 

   usually podcasting and errors as files or 

   like the story of them it's very it's still 

   into the anglophone world it's only from the 

   first world perspective and they forget 

   like all these tiny things are happening and 

   this is very interesting it's like it's been 

   forever this show it's a news sarcastic kind 

   of show it's not an academic one um but 

   the interesting thing that they also use radio 

   for places they could not get to like 

   someone would not get like internet or like 

   permanent internet electricity whatever they 

   have video so i feel like this is a great 

   example of a tool and projects that are like 

   100 thinking on who's gonna hear how it's gonna 

   hear it where it's gonna hear it um when 

   i was making my vodkas i decided to make it 

   in spanish like there's all least the reason 

   that i think i'm funny i'm more intelligent 

   in spanish uh which is like the little 

   joke that goes uh but also um i was thinking 

   on and when when i was like deciding the 

   language and deciding to do it in spanish i was 

   thinking like in what they are hearing are 

   they using their cell phones do they have 

   mac products probably not so much uh i feel 

   like uh the apple i don't know if we will 

   name brands but the fruit brand the apple brand 

   um it wasn't a big thing it was really 

   hard to get it like until like recent years 

   at least in chile like and still like there's 

   a very heavy tax on who have it or not have 

   it and and kind of a money gatekeeping so 

   you have to think about like who is hearing 

   where is hearing what tools are using uh it's 

   gonna be radio or not and that give you 

   that freedom and that way of working with i'm 

   i feel i'm rumbling around but um it's just 

   i get excited when i think about this uh i 

   remember i have a professor in high school 

   that he was teaching kids from uh southern part 

   of chile that were living in like uh 

   indigenous communities that were like a bar so 

   they weren't able to go to school every day 

   they were he was teaching over radio how to 

   read to these kids they will have this radio 

   program teaching how to read and i was like 

   he had to travel every time to the southern 

   to to near to the place where this community 

   lives so he could do the radio and as i grew 

   up and i started working with podcasts and 

   and learning about uh the rsss i was like 

   uh anybody could be teaching those kids like 

   if you have someone that could be able to 

   pick that feed and put it on the radio signal 

   you could have everyone in the world teaching 

   whatever is necessary to escape not only 

   how to read there is like so many possibilities 

   um and this is coming back to what do 

   we need to teach yes and learn yeah yeah and 

   and what matters the most could make like 

   like this teacher he was a high school teacher 

   this year who was traveling every weekend 

   and he was like taking like night buses 

   all night buses to get to the place he did 

   the radio program um it might not be necessary 

   like you will have so many people you will 

   have volunteers that are like from the 

   comfort of their home teaching this kid a lot 

   of skills that you could teach by audio and 

   and there are tools like it's hard to imagine 

   how to teach someone how to read using 

   the radio um but it's possible and it's these 

   cases show that it's possible we are just 

   not thinking of it because we are not 

   thinking outside the box which minimal computer 

   let us think outside the box when we're 

   making the the fourth question and now the the 

   new questions um and i feel like it's like 

   three questions like what we did um the 

   second one that that uh you mentioned and what 

   do we need to change what we need to change 

   and for who we're making the project uh let 

   us think outside the box and and think on 

   the material world that it's around or 

   hacking outside or coding outside or softwares 

   outside our fancy equipment 

   when we have women 

   and yeah I feel like and all of that 

   was like 

   part of 

   when I started into the documentaries 

   when I started seeing podcasting 

   when I started like seeing and I 

   started like thinking on okay this is 

   all these things are happening 

   and kind of click in my head 

   yeah well okay 

   this is great so so i think 

   we're we are expanding on our 

   conversation last week quite a bit 

   um let me see what else do we 

   should we try to pick up here 

   so I we could come back so I'm 

   looking at some of the places where 

   we have a lot of bullet points 

   and um that's where we could come back I 

   think it's in this area toward like late in 

   the conversation when we were talking about 

   the problems introduced now things that 

   are different now than when we first had 

   these conversations in 2022 and one of them 

   of course is the availability of ai and 

   people telling us that oh ai will be your 

   teacher now and it's you know maybe it's cheap 

   and it's affordable and um i think we have 

   some maybe strong feelings about that now 

   um should we uh come back to um to some 

   of that i was talking i remember about um 

   the problems that I mainly been reading about 

   where the big AI companies harvesting 

   textual without accreditation and kind of 

   pulling them into a black box. They're applying 

   very powerful natural language processing 

   tools that we are not permitted to see. 

   And at the same time, like digesting that 

   material and giving it back to us um to 

   consume and in conversation and um that for 

   many artists and creators and writers and 

   thinkers around the world this is changing 

   their livelihood it's changing the basis 

   of their work and for us as digital humanities 

   people it's raising a question of the 

   kinds of tools that we want to use and um 

   yeah like what what do we do about it like 

   you know to some extent we rely on the 

   things that big tech gives us and in the 

   minimal computing context um perhaps there i 

   mean one of the things we talked about last 

   week was well ease of access is a priority 

   that like if ai is available maybe we 

   want to use it to help right help with things 

   because it's the easiest you don't have 

   to it has a low barrier of entry to have a 

   conversation with a chat bot and let it 

   handle some of the technical things for you 

   um and then there's the problem of yeah 

   every time you're using it it it's using you 

   and your community and 

   all of this. So, yeah. 

   Yeah, I think it's very important 

   to talk about post-2021, 2022, 

   where this talk was originally situated to 

   the present time. I'm thinking about it in 

   two ways. One of it is still the same 

   system that we face in the Global South where 

   everything is shipped down to the global 

   south in terms of technology infrastructure 

   like the dh method dh tools we hardly had 

   any contribution from the global south 

   developing or contributing a theory or concept 

   or software or two so the same embrace i 

   call it warm embrace that we had with the 

   knowledge shipment or knowledge transfer 

   or knowledge mediation in the global south 

   from the west is still the same lens. I'm 

   thinking about the AI in that space. It's 

   still from the west, if I should say that. 

   So I think that will be a way to, I mean, 

   I'm thinking about it if I have to put myself 

   in the global south right now on spot. So 

   I think the first would be how do I know 

   how to use it to help me navigate what coding 

   I should do if I want to learn DH and DH 

   is saying I should learn how to code the hack 

   and yak and the debates even in the West. 

   So I think some of us will quickly take it 

   up and learn the tools and use it to write 

   CSS code or HTML code without really knowing 

   what the code is all about. And if that 

   works, then we can run with it. So it's still 

   the same method of we want to learn the DH 

   tools, DH method, even though we don't have 

   power or opportunity to contribute to the 

   development, but we are the receiving hand. 

   We want to use it. So, and I think beyond 

   the hype of AI, it's still going to be the 

   same systemic structure. We want to use it 

   to learn those things. I remember reading 

   Rebecca Rissam's iteration or provocation about 

   why she had to learn coding, even though 

   the debate has always been you don't need 

   to learn coding but she when she was working 

   on our post post -colonial studies um the 

   wb du bois projects she needed a hands on some 

   of those things that they were building 

   for her and she she wanted to get control she 

   wanted to contribute to the building so 

   she had to go learn java not not just css java 

   and she's way more better for it now. I 

   mean, over the years, of course, the progression, 

   it's not one year, but over the years, 

   so she can build on her own. She can 

   contribute to a project where the technical team 

   will be there. She could say something about 

   a project. So I think that is the way- 

   This is the surprising position where the 

   digital humanist stands up to the know-it-all 

   technician who has the sort of supreme 

   authority on how your project is supposed to be 

   made. and you say no i see how your tool 

   works here and i need that to change yeah yeah 

   and that's part of that change conversation 

   we were just having right i think this is 

   why it's important to code is so that but 

   when when somebody like us and i i'm hoping 

   is this in digital black atlantic is is this 

   one of her contributions so she talks about 

   this or just are anything most recent 

   chapter maybe 2026 or 2025 okay so this is very 

   current stuff for her yeah it looks like 

   the way we are talking about it so she also 

   was like making that kind of provocation 

   movement so it's not like you learn everything 

   there is to know about a programming language 

   but you learn how it affects your digital 

   humanities project and you become an expert 

   on this area that those those tech people 

   have completely they have blind spots 

   they're not looking they don't understand that 

   tool is hurting people here right or this 

   yeah and i know you said the same background 

   if you were to share with us you also have 

   to do your primor tech tech thing on your 

   own i know you have some insight to share 

   before we move to a console oh me about learning 

   on my own so for me on this and i probably 

   did talk about this in the ai summary 

   would not pick it up so for me i started doing 

   digital humanities, just I've been a 

   traditional humanities scholar. I was an English 

   literature PhD, and I work with Brit 

   Lit. So I am like kind of, my 

   background is not very Global South at all. 

   But I just wanted to go into the 

   archives and help make an edition of 

   a 19th century woman writer's letters and 

   productions, like her literary work. I just 

   wanted to I wanted them to be available and 

   you know at first there was a print book 

   project but she wrote so much and she's not 

   canon so the big publishing companies around 

   2007 2008 weren't going to produce that and 

   that was with a big scholar in my field like 

   wanting to take on that edition and I was 

   just going to help so I raised my hand at a 

   conference and said can I help with this 

   project and he said i'm sorry the publishing 

   company has shut it down and that's really how 

   i began my journey in digital humanities 

   was what and i was learning there's these 

   workshops on the tei and there's workshops on 

   like digitizing texts and i found like oh 

   there's a whole scholarly method here and over 

   the next few years i got ****** into it 

   and it felt like magic oh i can And I can make 

   a document data model of my own that reflects 

   where I want to see her personal life 

   writing in connection with the plays that she's 

   producing, which are very kind of artificial, 

   very structured and formal. And then 

   she's got these other literary genres. Wait, 

   I'm going to need help. We need other people 

   to help. I can't do this alone was another 

   lesson. And like, what do I need? What do 

   I want? It was 2013 -ish, 2014, when I got 

   started. And I don't know if we were using the 

   phrase minimal computing then, but where 

   I'm situated, I'm at regional university 

   campuses. I was never at like a research hub, 

   but I always had like interesting little 

   projects and it's sort of like, you know, but I 

   didn't have to worry so much as maybe others 

   do. in maybe the research r1 context where 

   i was situated in the regional campuses if 

   you do something digital and you can bring 

   students with you everybody's very excited 

   because your little campus now has something 

   to say and something to build with it and 

   some things might be more possible in that 

   sort of regional comprehensive context which 

   is more about education primarily and where 

   nobody's expecting you to do like the best 

   research or the fastest research or producing 

   the most books. So I got to have a little 

   adventure with my life as an academic because 

   I'm, you know, a little bit off center. 

   And my experience of minimal 

   competing was simply, 

   oh don't rely on tech support don't rely 

   on regular funding what are the tools that 

   you can use that don't cost and so that 

   leads to things like code repositories on 

   github possibly codeberg now if that's 

   strong enough right or like learning git and 

   version control on your own that's a huge 

   lift oh that means i have to learn 

   command line just enough yeah um I can make a 

   little shell script sometimes with help, 

   right? But I'm not a computer scientist. 

   I can teach students how I think 

   about modeling documents with code 

   and get them doing the same things. 

   And it was kind of an adventure of, 

   oh, learning to code meant learning. 

   It meant that, oh, I can do these things 

   low cost or no cost. It wasn't like if I do 

   no code, I'm going to have to contend with 

   broken plugins and people I can't rely on. 

   Right. And it's kind of that simple. But 

   it's it's even more than that. I mean, the code 

   gives me creative license or it gives me 

   and us like an opportunity to build some of 

   our own tools and share them with others. 

   And for me, that that's a potential energy 

   that's more exciting than just studying 

   literature and writing about it. so like when I 

   say oh digital humanities it changed my life 

   it did it's more exciting now uh but yeah 

   like my minimal context is it's exciting 

   because I'm pinched like I don't have access 

   that other people do so I guess that's that's 

   my simple yeah how does like the AI affect 

   how does AI affect that like how have you 

   seen it because like you have this the 

   students coining and also like like it's tempting 

   like sometimes you have a you're like 

   spending hours and you're having like one error 

   in one line and you cannot see it and 

   you're like oh my god and you know there is you 

   know there is a an ai available that could 

   give you something in five seconds and so 

   i do like i think that's okay like like to 

   use it as a friend to your code like But then 

   it's kind of a question where, you know, 

   and I've had these weird relationships with 

   AI over the past year because everyone around 

   me, of course, is saying you should use 

   AI, right? And you should tell us all about 

   it. It's important for the university that 

   you show you're using AI. It's like, okay. 

   So definitely using it to help locate syntax 

   errors. We would do syntax validation in 

   a good code editor, too. Like I, you know, 

   it's like one does not handwrite code, right? 

   But then you start like to notice your AI 

   bot has an assumption about your code. And 

   if you start asking it bigger questions like, 

   okay, I want to make this data structure 

   or I want to make a data structure and I want 

   you to figure it out for me. that's where 

   you start to lose the lose the creative magic 

   it's more exciting to use ai when you're 

   like oh no no no i really want this and you 

   have to help me because i'm stuck here right 

   that's one thing but the other side of it 

   is i don't know what to do um can you help 

   and then i get the same kind of glossy stuff 

   or even it'll give me back something i 

   don't want and then have a fight with it but 

   then at some point i start losing time so i 

   think it it starts ******* my time and energy 

   and changing my way of thinking and and 

   for that reason sort of pulling away back to 

   the material world might be good like maybe 

   i want to sit down with pen and paper and 

   like mark my tax and figure out what what do 

   i want and you know go from there um i i 

   don't have a good answer for this, but the 

   place I'm moving with AI right now is to try 

   to minimize it. So that is relevant where I 

   have a little research project right now that 

   I'm going to be talking about, or I have 

   started talking about it at conferences. My 

   students want to learn about AI and I want 

   to find a responsible way of working with it. 

   With a very big old project like mine at 

   the Digital Mitford. People come and go. We've 

   had generations of students come and go. 

   There's a lot of unevenness, a lot of 

   unfinished work, and it gets put aside for more 

   glamorous projects like my Frankenstein project 

   and other things or even this AI thing. 

   And what it would be nice is to have an AI 

   humbly learn from our project standards, give 

   it like a local customized AI that understands 

   what we need to do and take some of the 

   heavy labor and speed that up for us what 

   because we're clear on what we want and what 

   we need to finish now my dream here is to 

   have this run totally on a desktop computer so 

   it doesn't need a data center and that it 

   also runs on things that the code that i know 

   how to write like i can write a schema i 

   can write some x path i can say these are the 

   relationships we're trying to build here's 

   some unfinished code help me finish it and 

   you know the other side of ai in where i work 

   with digital scholarly editions is the 

   really powerful stuff that says here's handwriting 

   up and down the sides of a page backwards 

   upside down sideways can you help with the 

   starter transcription of that like there's 

   some amazing but that's also very customized 

   and the sort of thing that humanity scholars 

   you don't just go cold to a chatbot to do 

   that you've built that little engine and 

   it's hard work to make it right so i think like 

   the place but is is this sort of like the 

   hard rewarding labor of customizing a thing 

   so that you change it for your specific 

   project i guess yeah that's where that's where 

   i am with it i i get it with with ai i see 

   the same as felix i feel like it's very done 

   in the global north kind of it's very centered 

   on their necessities it's very centered 

   in their material like i remember like early 

   chat gpt like like getting information in 

   spanish i like to experiment with it every 

   now and then i will ask questions or like you 

   know like news or stuff like that to see how 

   it's like picking up information in other 

   languages in my cases i take it in spanish 

   which is my native language um and so uh i i 

   check that up because i kind of worry in a 

   way that all the information and all the 

   feedback it's like it could be in spanish but 

   it could be just translated and not be like 

   like originally coming from from this point 

   of view and i feel like that it's like something 

   that it's like a little bit tricky but 

   then again with coding like i i think discusses 

   like i i wrote it down in there in the 

   document uh but something interesting about 

   coding coding believes that english is the 

   lingua franca and it is not that's its foundation 

   and that is foundation so you need a base 

   in english to be able to construct and to 

   able to think because you're when you start 

   programming you're basically thinking in 

   three different languages one that it's like 

   the logic of this language is not made coding 

   then you have to learn the language that 

   the logic is working with and then you have to 

   code so there are like so many steps missing 

   in in in that i like i remember my first 

   coding classes were in 2022 because i I jump 

   from like podcasting and like more simple 

   things and then I jump into like oh now I need 

   to record code and I remember like the 

   first weeks of like learning I was learning 

   Java I was learning like something difficult 

   in general and I remember having struggles 

   like thinking sometimes in commands because I 

   will think the name in Spanish and then I 

   translate it but I don't translate it in the 

   one that is used for coding so I will use 

   another signer and I will why is red why the 

   the dot is not moving from one corner to the 

   other one and i couldn't understand like 

   doing like like movements like that and so ai 

   can be helpful in that way for someone that 

   doesn't know a big base in english and wants 

   to do their own project and it's like where 

   do i start and how do i start but i think 

   we need different ai tools than the ones we're 

   given right even the ones were given for 

   free even right yeah then is it for free like 

   you yeah no it's not really it's an addiction 

   it's an addiction model right you get 

   more and more dependent yeah and then they they 

   ask you for money to get more of something 

   that you are feeding so so basically you 

   own stuff that you're giving it but also you 

   have to pay to get the feedback of the things 

   that you own and you're giving to the AI. 

   Yeah, I think we should step back a second 

   here and also recognize this is something 

   the TEI community has been having discussions 

   about internationalization and where 

   there's a portion there are members of our 

   community like Till Growler and like others. 

   Like it's a small group that they're digitizing 

   um like newspapers periodicals printed 

   in arabic but printing in arabic if this 

   goes back pre-computer that's like a right to 

   left ligature language and the printing 

   machines never got it right in the way that 

   it was sort of locally expressed and our 

   computer code systems are built like the text 

   encoding like the encoding of characters 

   character encoding like ascii and unicode was 

   always like never appropriate for that kind 

   of language structure and so like when the 

   whole machinery is wrong and yet you can 

   still archive and code because the machinery 

   that produced the text was readable it's 

   like you're looking at this history of machinery 

   in a state of cultural compromise um 

   and it's kind of fascinating like to listen 

   to um like somebody like Till talk about um 

   you know like what that means and like what 

   kinds of projects they're able to make out 

   of it and you know and like what what do 

   we do how do we change the tools these are 

   huge questions that don't have answers but 

   what do we need to change starts like getting 

   a getting to be bigger and bigger now maybe 

   in the mid 2020s then you know can i jump 

   in and connect this um important thing you 

   just raised about the history of the machines 

   that produce the scholarly traditions. 

   I kind of have this kind 

   of trace model in my mind, 

   which is a critical way to think about it. 

   From the global north, 

   the debate, 

   or the trends, 

   or the shifts from one form of scholarship 

   within the DH to another form, to another 

   form. I'll make it more simple. It was usually 

   called the digital edition. We want to make 

   sure the Emily Dickinson archive is online. 

   Yeah. 

   Now, it's into digitization. We want to 

   ensure all newspapers are digitized from 

   microfilm, which is different from solid edition, 

   from microfilm to all the dissertation 

   pipelines so that machine learning algorithm 

   can access them for textual analysis. 

   That's another paradigm. and now we have the 

   paradigm of using the ai cloud to really 

   help you to do the coding as well as do the 

   building of the technical skills and as well 

   as building the projects where are we in 

   the global south in all these paradigm 

   shifts we really started digitizing like you 

   mentioned if we go back to national archives 

   in nigeria are they really scanned let 

   alone digitized into um vectors or what 

   abeddings that can be used to train anything so 

   i'm kind of thinking i don't know where we 

   are right yeah and the global notes moved 

   over a decade i can track it this is 2026 

   2016, 

   the goal would be scholarly tradition, 

   so I'm not thinking that we're now in 2026, 

   that that's what Global North is doing with 

   the age, especially when it's branching out 

   to sub-disciplines like cultural analytics, 

   computational humanities, 

   everybody's talking, they start reading. 

   Are we there? 

   Where is the landscape 

   of the global south dh i mean from the 

   typical example you gave on the arabic so we 

   still have that kind of challenge back in 

   other global south countries in india and 

   the rest where is the landscape even within 

   the minimal computing concentration yeah 

   that's a good question i want us to think 

   about connecting with what matters to do in 

   the global south now yeah yeah i know that 

   i feel yeah it's i i hate to use this word 

   i hate to use a slow i think it's our stages 

   but also i feel stages are like it's not 

   something that it's about level it's something 

   that it's about the not media or just it's 

   not linear uh so i don't like to put like 

   like this global south is behind the global 

   south is dealing with other problems right 

   so that's why we're taking more time in 

   different things um it's it's complicated when 

   when you're trying to put it uh versus high 

   to emoji again like minimal computer let 

   us to think about digital projects digital 

   necessities not on a scale of how advanced 

   we are correct we're on the scales of the 

   necessities which i i really love that um but 

   i think like like what is happening i've 

   been seeing in chile for example there's been 

   a wave of a lot of uh programming like there 

   is an r group of programming in chile like 

   sort ladies or our ladies in chile get 

   together there's also like it's a linkedin for 

   the group i'm in the group i never i i 

   haven't been able to jump into one because like 

   the three hour difference is a killer when 

   you're trying to get time to to get it but 

   i've seen like there are like so many new 

   initiatives on like learning how to go learning 

   tools um i cannot remember now but there 

   is a woman a professor in is it in stanford 

   she now has a group for the age in spanish 

   she collects people that want to teach 

   different tools so she's teaching omegas in 

   spanish she's teaching like buoyant in spanish 

   she's teaching different things and like 

   she's inviting and she's doing it out of her 

   heart kind of um and and it's a whole group 

   and they have like this seminar and it's 

   called like like like the like humanities in 

   for like spanish speakers and it's like 

   all those those efforts that are are coming 

   into and i feel like the translation of tools 

   it's something very necessarily and tools 

   are like no the fanciest tools are like the 

   ones that cover the necessities and like 

   let us like play with it and advance with it 

   and also control it so i mean that connects 

   to something felix and i were talking 

   about with like ant conch and voyant being 

   like so quickly accessible and you can 

   see so much and you can get in and change 

   the tool and yeah yeah yeah so that sounds 

   like another yet another example of us 

   yes oh you have like also like the and i 

   have to put it here programming historian 

   they have like they have even like portuguese 

   they have they have so many with like 

   even french uh spanish so you have like all 

   these uh tutorials so i feel like the kind of 

   the moment that we are sitting in it's like 

   taking control over our tools taking 

   control over what is happening i think that is 

   job in the global south how we take control 

   how we reclaim all of these and make it 

   ours or how we reclaim the basics so we could 

   make our own projects under our own logic 

   um i love what you just said making our own 

   projects under our own logic like we should 

   like put a big it's really good yeah but 

   yes i i remember reading on um this is on 

   design like humanities and design and ux designer 

   i cannot remember i read this for this 

   design class um on african-american digital 

   design and how the websites and how like 

   everything looks different than the white 

   green background but the powerful color and 

   imagery and and even though it's not that the 

   tendency it's not like the polish look that 

   it's imposed to us to make and to create 

   designing for like the community take it 

   taking the tools and making your own taking 

   the the possibility of like creating a website 

   and making your own i feel like that it's 

   it's something and make it available in 

   your own language i think i think of my 

   parents like they don't speak they miss so many 

   stuff kind of and they were also missing 

   them like kind of kind of that it's like the 

   feeling like they miss hearing like my mom 

   and my dad saying like intelligent stuff 

   not only intelligent but like having like 

   everything they know and they also miss so 

   much information that it's available and 

   accessible for so many people but only 

   because they don't fit on what these tools 

   and what this information is made of yeah i 

   get a little bit emotional on that sorry 

   no that's actually i think that's the the 

   stuff that makes us emotional is what matters 

   to say here now yeah yeah and i feel 

   like like uh minimal computer let us i can't 

   let us think us about outside the box let 

   us build something robust build a bridge 

   yeah build a bridge build a bridge yeah 

   so about that bridge building i think 

   the ai summary got this just didn't 

   get it like so so let's get it again 

   what are you talking about with that 

   but uh i feel like we we jump into that like 

   in different moments when we were talking 

   about DH practitioner in general like so 

   builders bridge builders um when we were taking 

   like the big cameras i'm like she's talking 

   about like the project that i was talking 

   like she's able to now navigate two worlds 

   she's able to talk to the tech guy and then 

   talk to the one who is doing the maybe the 

   cultural interpretation or the cultural necessities 

   for a project and that is a huge example 

   of what what we do as digital humanities 

   practitioners we are in the middle of two 

   worlds we're in the middle of the physical and 

   digital like even while we were talking 

   about like the books and having physical books 

   and and work with physical materials and you 

   have theater projects are like they need 

   so much physical work because everything is 

   not online everything is not like there and 

   you have to build from that so it's like it's 

   like this this stress hole that we are like 

   sitting in uh and i i enjoy that and i think 

   like like minimal computer it is like 

   thinking on how we create a base how we create 

   a base for a project how we think about all 

   that we need how we get to the other side 

   all together and and recognize every piece 

   that it made that possible but i want to jump 

   on what do you think about this bridge idea 

   so i mean it as we've been talking this 

   morning i feel like a thing that emerged for 

   me much more clearly now is the physical 

   groundwork that that foundation of our 

   bridge is the world we physically live in and 

   the worlds we move through when we travel 

   and like you know where our communities 

   are living and what they can access what do 

   they have what do they want what do they 

   need um that as we're trying to find the 

   right things to teach that knowing where 

   they are even if we're going to teach them 

   in an online context how will they access 

   us right how will they reach for us is there 

   something they can download that's not 

   enormous that like but that's also something 

   they can pick up and find interesting 

   and um connects with things they care about 

   um yeah it's like meeting in that like being 

   aware of the physical groundwork and its 

   limits and yeah seems seems very important 

   what do you think about this bridge do 

   you see yourself as a bridge builder 

   i see a bridge behind you yeah yeah i 

   think in the context of the global 

   south dh has been a bridge i i i made a 

   connection before i mean earlier this morning 

   we're with elisa that the kind of training 

   education in the community um serve as 

   a bridge for a couple of us to gain access 

   to um global north education in in grad 

   programs a lot of us moved in through primarily 

   the training we got from summer schools 

   and conferences in nigeria that stimulates 

   our interest we we now when we write sop i 

   can mention buoyant not to the degree of 

   how much i can use it but i can mention it 

   in my sop and and that that kind of moved 

   me into loyola um in in that kind of foundation 

   i already have with summer school and 

   conferences. So I think DH serves as a bridge 

   in that sense of human capacity development 

   and kind of transfer of knowledge from 

   global south to global north. The second 

   thing why DH serves as a bridge is I'm strongly 

   believing that it's maybe not in the 

   full scale but in the scale of connecting to 

   the community that hones the data, that 

   hones the manuscript that hones the history. 

   So DH would normally serve as a bridge for 

   DH practitioners to now work with the community. 

   Like we mentioned last week, the Muktu 

   software was built on the basis of how the 

   community see the history and the tool was 

   built on that. So it wasn't like off-the-shelf 

   tool that was implanted into a community 

   of users. It was a community of users that 

   built it and the purpose was to allow the 

   community with the DH practitioners as well as 

   the community to work together and build 

   digital objects or digital artifacts through 

   that too. So I'm thinking that would be on the 

   educational access of educating either 

   within an outside country or where the DH is 

   located. The other one is the access to connecting 

   the community with the DH practitioners 

   as well as the, which might still be a long 

   way coming because Because like I mentioned, 

   the Texas projects of massacre in Texas, 

   where the Professor Amy was able to work 

   closely with the lived experiences of people 

   who, one way or the other, witnessed the 

   massacre or they could give a history about it. 

   And she wasn't building a project as a 

   professor from the office. She built the project 

   with the community that the massacre took 

   place. how much of that we have in global 

   south would be a question but i think that is 

   what i mean by bridge that's the way i see 

   it that we now begin to engage the community 

   of people who hones the project i mean 

   who hones the history we want to preserve uh 

   we we tell them the story um we tell them 

   the technical skills that we can use and we 

   allow them to contribute to also open up to 

   say or we can contribute the third bridge 

   would be going forward i mean would be the dh 

   practitioners from the global south also 

   contributing to tech developments that's 

   another bridge i'm thinking about um which in 

   in the first decade or so what we do is to 

   use the tools and being able to see the 

   limitation or the strength but not amenable or 

   applicable to our own data set so the question 

   will not be DH practitioners in the global 

   south also contributing to enough tech 

   development or existing changes in existing 

   tech developments that are all undergoing. A 

   case study would be a PhD candidate in UK, 

   Augustine Fariola, was very instrumental 

   back then in Nigeria. He had philosophy 

   background so his epistemology mentor skill set 

   was profound so he was able to get his 

   training in nigeria move to the uk for phd now 

   he works with rockwell in canada um building 

   the voyance tools consortium which is uh 

   another body beyond the two developers but 

   contributors who had used the tool for 

   researches and they want to say this is what 

   will find out and so he's the one anchoring 

   that because he has a background in philosophy 

   he has a training in DH and he's on his 

   PhD program so he was able to work with 

   Rockwell Jeffrey Rockwell building the community 

   side of it beyond the two and getting 

   feedback so he runs monthly or quarterly 

   workshop on DH on on voyants I mean for all 

   week with Rockwell for the global south. 

   Nigerians, Cameroonians, so they come together 

   and the end goal of such project was you 

   have to do a project with voyants and you have 

   to tell us what you did and tell us how 

   to improve it. And so that is his own goal. 

   Another case study I would refer to is Yaku 

   James from University of Kansas at Lawrence 

   building African DH. He runs a symposium in 

   Ghana. Last year Alex was there um and a 

   couple of people would always travel down to 

   ghana to do african dh now african dh in the 

   in in the african soil uh even though it 

   works in it works at university of cancer but 

   it's pushing towards domestication of the 

   dh in the land where i mean in the where the 

   research is coming out from not just so 

   you had worked with um learning wood films 

   but just like we have hollywood nollywood 

   films um where they were not in digital form 

   so you had to go for posters um banners and 

   flyers you know nigeria when we produce 

   film we usually put the posters on the streets 

   the new film is out so from the poster 

   you could know the viewing station i don't 

   know if it's view station here you know it 

   should be viewing station like where people 

   watch football or sports so people also go 

   to watch movies in in the center not in your 

   room not in your house because you don't 

   have the luxury so from the posters and 

   banners on the street um on electric posts 

   wherever they paste it you know the time the 

   show will be on viewing just like in the 

   theater in in the west theater you go to theater 

   too but this one is like a a deal in a 

   small room that people come together pay you 

   pay then you you watch it so he's trying 

   to digitize um nollywood pre maybe post post 

   um civil war or post -independence or pre 

   -independence was trying to go through the 

   history of nonnywood in nigeria and the second 

   project which seems to be very interesting 

   is the um nigerian literature in the 

   markets we call it market literature so there 

   are histories that um connect the dots um 

   be fortunate to be 1948 that was the first 

   african nigerian novel would i say nigerian 

   novel not not the first but i mean typical 

   of teens fall apart which was a product 

   from out of darkness joseph conrad it was a 

   ph it was an english student from university 

   of ibadan which was formerly university of 

   london in nigeria and she he read teens 

   fall apart sorry he read heart of darkness and 

   he was hungry the way um joseph conrad 

   depicted africa as hard as black i mean as 

   darkness right yeah yeah so in retrospect he 

   wrote his first novel things fall apart uh 

   which seems to be summary is saying we were 

   we had our culture we had our civilization 

   before you people came before things fell 

   apart so and he took that from um the poem 

   turning and turning in this welding uh um 

   second coming second coming that's from yates 

   yeah wb yates so it took the line this fall 

   apart from the second coming um that we 

   already had our life going on we have local 

   administrations we have cultural practices 

   they were stable you might call it non 

   -civilized but they were stable they were they 

   were documented but things fell apart when 

   the ****** came and introduced civilization 

   christianization and commercialization the 

   three cities we usually study in history and 

   that changed the dynamic so his own goal for 

   yoko james was to document the pamphlet 

   literature from the market um there were small 

   pamphlets people drop it in the market um 

   maybe poems and thereabouts before we now have 

   a standard um form of writing so that's also 

   serves as a bridge building project even 

   though he's a western scholar trained in canada 

   works um universal of cancers, but it's 

   going back to see what it can document and 

   digitize, maybe with resources from the West or 

   resource or no resources or manpower. And it 

   runs the African DH symposium every year to 

   support that kind of move. So DH in the global 

   South will usually be a bridge in those 

   spectrum, I've explained, if we're captured. 

   wow that's immense what you just described 

   because it kind of moves through time 

   but if you're following a scholar who is 

   like organized african digital humanities 

   and that's so important um because 

   it's the bridge that he and others like him 

   and you right like our building seems 

   to be about, yeah, using those tools that 

   started in the West or the North, however 

   you describe that, and changing them, 

   educating with them even before you 

   change them, but also in the process 

   of educating, recognizing the 

   problems, and deciding with other people 

   what you want to do and what matters now 

   yeah do you think it's our bridges are in 

   danger or vulnerable to um i'll just stop 

   with like vulnerable and if so to what yeah 

   yeah go ahead no no i think like 

   it's just i don't like to be 

   a little fight completely AI. 

   I think sometimes that could be a 

   bridge destroyer because it takes a lot 

   of the communications that happen. 

   Okay, what can be a communication? 

   The communication, like creating 

   multicultural projects and 

   just add an AI and the AI will 

   be the... Oh, so AI, our bridges are vulnerable 

   to AI. Yeah, okay. i think in that way 

   in a way that that for for making these 

   bridges you need communication you need to see 

   each other kind of and i feel like it's 

   dangerous when we start like only seeing the 

   machine kind of um we have been talking a lot 

   about the human resource the human factor 

   in everything we do the human factor in minimal 

   computing um how the human factor have 

   changed our way to work like how we thinking 

   about others how we seeing other people work 

   in projects and and how we we like like 

   your example that you said like i want to 

   participate in that edition and and but that 

   was because you were like you have an inquitude 

   and you have another one like communicated 

   the same and you were like oh we need to 

   do something about it and then jumping into 

   and and felix also was like working in in 

   archives and going around the globe like 

   learning and going into conference and 

   trying to manage a way to communicate to 

   showcase what he was doing and and and in in 

   my case also i was like looking for like 

   how how i could share this knowledge and 

   how this could be meaningful for for a group 

   of people that usually overlook on um 

   in in the term of technology i mean the 

   world of broadcasting so and so i feel like 

   sometimes like ai cool it's like could 

   replace that communication because it will 

   give you all the answers and yeah it's 

   so authoritative someone else yes so 

   confident yeah yes so confident and will 

   give you the answers you want not the the 

   one that that you need to hear kind of 

   like we could ask chat gpt to write a paper 

   discussion on the like did you feel that 

   tension because i did like oh take these 

   bullet point notes and at any point any of 

   the three of us and i thought of this i 

   thought seriously because we're under like 

   really high pressure time constraint would you 

   turn this into a dialogue and between me 

   and felix and consuelo and then we would 

   look at it and like there was a part of me 

   that was like i was almost like no like it 

   was sort of erupting from my gut like we 

   must not do that but like why do i why do i 

   feel that way i think we have good reason 

   but like for this article to be re-digested 

   for us by ai was like that's why we were 

   so upset right like oh my god and and that 

   thing that that is the communication we we 

   don't say we we're not complacent to you 

   to say like whatever the other one wants to 

   hear we're like sharing different perspective 

   or view and i feel like ai will be like 

   a little bit of ******* that part of 

   building our bridges like making um artificial 

   kind of like artificial bridges not human 

   vision yes and and we need that and i think 

   that that's dangerous because i feel 

   like we're finally opening we're finally 

   talking about it i feel like in the last 10 

   years we started like like finally i mean 

   a little bit more but finally saying like 

   hey like we are making like the humanities 

   from the periphery kind of and i feel like 

   that hey could be lost so quick when we 

   we stop here and we stop like looking for 

   asking questions to someone that will not 

   necessarily give us what we want who is 

   machine or something whose machines get to 

   remember who we are yes yes and and and i 

   feel that like they go tell me i don't know 

   they could tell me that chile has i mean 

   it has the best internet in in the continent 

   and they call it and that's um conosur 

   **** i forgot the oh oh my god sorry i um 

   the the conosur the the little triangle 

   behind i cannot remember this is happening 

   when you're like working in multiple languages 

   you're bilingual not bilingual um but 

   what it meant is like chile have in other 

   american countries chile has like the best 

   internet but that doesn't mean that the best 

   connection but that doesn't mean that 

   that connection is the best in all of chile 

   so the ai will tell me like oh yeah you 

   know how like the engine they have like 

   the most advanced they have the most 

   bandwidth it's gonna be everything you 

   want to you could have 4k images on your 

   web page and every you will be able to 

   see it everywhere but then you get there 

   and you go to like the north or you go to 

   the southern part and then you don't have 

   like even like like 45 minutes from the main 

   city uh for the main cities like you don't 

   have that reliable of internet necessarily 

   so you will not be able to see it and how 

   you know that it's happening if you talk 

   with someone that is in there you open your 

   eyes and you find someone that will keep 

   you sincere answers and then you're able to 

   make a robust project that will be able to 

   cross the digital barriers i don't know 

   how to call it but they they will be 

   able to jump the gap in the digital barriers 

   that exists in our title the digital 

   divide we experience those divides locally 

   and i feel like like that happened 

   when you lose the heat you will have yes 

   the best internet and then you will 

   find that it's not the best 

   internet everywhere it's a proportion 

   following podcast is intended for 

   mature audiences oh my god my 

   cell phone just put that on okay 

   well it's almost like a little 

   example the podcast is intended for 

   mature audiences with 

   potentially poor internet 

   oh my god yes i just have it like far away 

   i don't know what what was that what do 

   you mean about this that i hear like 

   probably cd sir is hearing us you know that 

   we're training siri i think we probably have 

   enough material i i think the next stage 

   of this where you know we will have a recording 

   um but we also um i'm gonna upload it into 

   kaltura the little example i sent was like 

   maybe 10 minutes of material but like i 

   recorded after a class so this this will take 

   longer but i don't think it's gonna take 

   days and stuff like it it works year every year 

   but even that like if we look at this i 

   don't know if you had a chance to look at it 

   but like if i share my screen real quick and 

   like are you seeing as we're probably seeing 

   a whole bunch of things right now but like 

   it's this is the zoom transcript in its 

   data format i was actually going to give this 

   to my students because we could make a little 

   homework exercise out of processing it 

   because like it's it's regularly patterned 

   and stuff but we're going get a very long string 

   like this and um i think we forgot the 

   idea that we had but which was like when we 

   start talking say consuelo or alisa we forgot 

   because conversation is like that but like 

   you know i can go through and rip out the 

   little time stamps but we're gonna get like 

   this flow of straight and and then we can 

   also watch ourselves but i kind of am wondering 

   okay what is the writing of this going to 

   be because we have like this textured document 

   very textured i'll just move it onto the 

   screen now um google wants me to pay more 

   money you can see that look at that pay money 

   and i'm like no i will not pay money for 

   you i will delete things before i pay money 

   yeah that is a problem we get the zoom bar 

   away but like we have i think this structure 

   like let's talk about that for a minute 

   because this might help us with like okay what 

   we're pounding we're mashing a thing together 

   like maybe it's like a fabric but like i 

   came up with i wrote a very silly introduction 

   that was meant to help cite people we need 

   we should cite more people i reached for 

   the one issue right but like we now have 

   digital black atlantic to cite we have jeffrey 

   rockwell's book on voyant we have um like 

   like grab your favorite people and like you 

   have projects like the digital nollywood and 

   stuff but like we can patch that stuff in 

   the way we do citations maybe not even up here 

   but like should we leave that maybe you 

   spoke of them in conversation so i think some 

   of that should go in here and like you know 

   we poke in the footnotes but like um we we 

   need to can i just delete this but like like 

   i almost wonder if we should pick this up 

   and move it to a separate document once we 

   get our like yes um like maybe we need a folder 

   but then so i think between you and me 

   consuelo and i i like i think we poked at this 

   document a little bit over the week and i 

   think felix came in toward the end and did 

   it but like we need to keep pieces like this 

   probably 

   yeah I think like we 

   could move around those 

   yeah it's going to be a mess is what's 

   going to happen I feel like we because it's 

   a Friday I don't think they're going to 

   be editing during the weekend right we 

   can't turn this around overnight no we 

   literally can't I mean should we write to 

   them and say no and tomorrow I have I have 

   the I'm hosting Douglas Day so I will be the 

   whole morning out and then I have to come 

   back and then I have a meeting there then 

   so yesterday I mean Friday it's looking hard 

   yeah I have my annual faculty evaluation 

   that I have to write 70% of it tonight but 

   after this meeting I go to campus I meet 

   with students and I have I'm meeting with 

   students all day I'm gonna get home at 6 and 

   have to do my faculty evaluation if I want 

   to keep my job well I know it's like we 

   have to do the annual and I put it off and 

   put it off and put it off and it's like oh 

   my god yeah so like we cannot give them back 

   an article tomorrow like I think we just 

   know we feel right I don't think they're 

   gonna be doing anything during the weekend 

   and we could like push it to monday manage 

   push it to monday and i'll find a little bit 

   of room there i i feel like um we have a 

   lot and maybe i don't think formatting is 

   most of what we do now because we what we 

   spoke is important yeah yes so and like i 

   wonder if we can put like sort of topic 

   headings on things like we sort of have those 

   and yeah okay so so so i feel like yeah um 

   weekend's gonna be busy uh what if i make a 

   google drive folder and then we can make 

   multiple documents in here because i think 

   we need to pick up the that ai pooped in our 

   document it we're going to pick that up and 

   move it aside we're writing right like so 

   we will have an idea yeah and then like we 

   keep the structured stuff and maybe should 

   i just put the transcript directly in like 

   paste it in like without the time stamps or 

   something like that like just put it directly 

   in and then we turn that into yeah 

   something pretty i think you will yeah we could 

   turn into something pretty we could move it 

   around we could put like subtitles maybe 

   we don't need to necessarily cut and we could 

   put an introduction like this is a discussion 

   we put like like we put subtitles like 

   a title we could put a little description 

   of like goals in there but we could say like 

   if you don't want to read and you want to 

   read everything you could like read everything 

   as a conversation oh so we do a little 

   summary yeah so kind of like like we could 

   we could continue because there is a lot of 

   continuity in the discussion that is happening 

   we could make subtitles when we think 

   like the topic is changing and it's evolving 

   so we could change the title put out your 

   description of what is coming kind of and 

   maybe we could add and we could add like an 

   introduction like a little place where we say 

   like this is a discussion it's meant to 

   be read like all together but if you want to 

   go jump into the specific section if you're 

   like interested in like discussion on AI, 

   like you could jump into like the 

   other. And I feel like that could 

   help us with the transitions. 

   We already know we're 

   adding two new questions, 

   right? You know, at least two, if 

   not three, actually three, right? 

   Three, three questions, yeah. 

   Yeah, so we add those in and those are 

   gonna give some new shape to it. I think it's 

   gonna be a beautiful thing to see, yeah. 

   So we're gonna try to push for this 

   to send out on Monday. do we write 

   to them or do we just stay quiet 

   we can stay quiet 

   because the key thing is they can't 

   afford to miss Humanity Computing's chapter 

   from the Gnosa we are taking hostage 

   because they really want this chapter that's 

   true I know they wrote us and they make 

   the effort for it so we can just keep quiet 

   so let's let's keep quiet but we do have a 

   beautiful thing yeah that's nice i always 

   feel bad keeping quiet but okay if they bite 

   us like hey i don't see it uh then we can 

   respond yes yes like i have a question about 

   this too should we talk frankly about our own 

   experience with ai in putting this chapter 

   together do we want to keep because it's 

   there in the conversation right do we keep it 

   or do we want to edit it out we go I feel 

   like we could keep it sort of yes like we could 

   keep like that attention like yeah we know 

   it's there like kind of like it's like we 

   we found ourselves actually very upset with 

   it at one point in preparing this because 

   we thought one thing of it and it provided 

   us another and it it was stealing our voices 

   I think that's an appropriate thing to say 

   it was stealing our yeah like the tone of it 

   the questions the memory of it yeah so so 

   we could talk about it i feel like we could 

   we could add in like on our frustrations and 

   our i don't know where we could even put it 

   toward the like app when we do the ai section 

   like maybe it comes at the end of it or 

   it's like a little addendum about like our 

   experience in designing this because it's a 

   little time capsule of our moment in 2026 

   and like the use of zoom and all of it no and 

   also i feel like it's it's a great example 

   of like we wanted to participate into the 

   world of ai and like and we see it failing just 

   one way it fails you know in the walls and 

   see like maybe sometimes we need to rely 

   on our minimal computing tools they're like 

   more they're more nice to us yeah i think 

   like we could do that i feel like uh the in 

   general the dialogue it's like very relatable 

   and i feel like we want to keep that up i'm 

   i'm thinking strictly this is an introduction 

   that probably students are gonna read yes 

   so i'm thinking that um minimal computing 

   like it's it's dry if you don't like speak 

   like like if we don't say what what we think 

   it's minimal computer's gonna be oh so 

   you're making your own robots kind of like 

   like it could go right there you know you're 

   making tiny robots that are more efficient 

   like no no no that's not what we're talking 

   about and i feel like it's inviting like 

   minimal computer is supposed to be inviting 

   to to everybody to participate where we're 

   to think about it so so i think it's it's 

   part of this academic relatable discussion 

   yeah i think my students should read this 

   whatever it turns out to be now that you 

   mention it yeah like everybody's students 

   should read this yeah and i think that's 

   probably what yeah they want for this book too 

   what they want to so yeah so that so let's 

   write this for our students and our people 

   yeah and i feel like they're gonna maybe 

   they're gonna like tuck them to the heart 

   that we felt the same temptation and the on 

   like ai and we have inspiration and why we 

   yeah yeah what we took and i feel like that 

   made us relatable also like yeah all right 

   well um is that do you think we'll be ready 

   i think we're ready yes we have this 

   recording in the recording we trust should i 

   shut the recording off it has to be shut off 

   in order for us to get it so here we go 

   and hit stop recording stop cloud reporting
</xml>