
<?xml-model href="../KewG_relax_ng.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    <metadata>
        <source>
            <title>Kew Gardens</title>
            <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
            <illustrator>Vanessa Bell</illustrator>
            <publisher>Hogarth Press</publisher>
            <pubDate>1927</pubDate>
            <format>Book</format>
            <archive>British Library</archive>
            <sourceLink/>
        </source>
        <edition>
            <editor>avr</editor>
            <consultant>ebb</consultant>
            <review>edm</review>
            <place>Penn State Behrend</place>
            <date>2021</date>
            <license>Public Domain</license>
        </edition>
    </metadata>


    <page n="1" facs="../docs/img/page1.jpg">
        <description resp="#edm"> Burnt maroon cover with a tan key-shape center with yellow
            squiggles with burnt maroon, and light bluish-grey speckling. The title font and
            information is the same thick typefaced font, almost like "Impact". </description>
        <line n="1"/>KEW GARDENS<line n="2"/>BY<line n="3"/>VIRGINIA WOOLF<line n="4"
            />DECORATIONS<line n="5"/>BY<line n="6"/>VANESSA BELL<line n="7"/>THE<line n="8"
        />HOGARTH PRESS</page>

    <page n="2" facs="../docs/img/page2.jpg">
        <description resp="#edm"> Off-white page with maroon dotting down the left-hand side. The
            writing on the page was the same burnt maroon as the cover. The font is in a more
            handwritten, storybook font. </description>
        <line n="1"/>Kew Gardens <line n="2"/>by <line n="3"/>Virginia <line n="4"/>Woolf <line
            n="5"/>decorated by Vanessa Bell <line n="6"/>published by the Hogarth Press </page>

    <page n="3" facs="../docs/img/page3.jpg">
        <description resp="#edm"> Plain off-white page with text centered and justified. </description>
        <line n="1"/>This edition, published in 1927, <line n="2"/>is limited to 500 numbered
        copies, <line n="3"/>of which this is number 150 </page>

    <page n="4" facs="../docs/img/page4.jpg">
        <description resp="#edm"> Kew Gardens is written at the top in a handwritten, storybook font.
            it is the top part of the border decoration that takes up the margins as well as the
            bottom half of the page. The designs are flowers and leaves painting in a simplisting,
            scroll-y style with black ink. </description>
        <line n="1"/>From the <shape>oval-shaped</shape>
        <nature type="plant">flower-bed</nature> there rose <line n="2"/>perhaps a hundred <nature
            type="plant">stalks</nature> spreading into <line n="3"/><shape>heart-shaped</shape> or
            <shape>tongue-shaped</shape>
        <nature type="plant">leaves</nature> half <line n="4"/>way up and unfurling at the tip
            <color>red</color> or <color>blue</color> or <line n="5"/><color>yellow</color>
        <nature type="plant">petals</nature> marked with spots of colour raised <line n="6"/>upon
        the surface; and from the <color>red</color>, <color>blue</color> or <color>yellow</color>
        <line n="7"/>gloom of the throat emerged a straight bar, <line n="8"/>rough with
            <color>gold</color> dust and slightly <shape>clubbed</shape>
        <line n="9"/>at the end. </page>

    <page n="5" facs="../docs/img/page5.jpg">
        <description resp="#edm"> At the top of the page, there is a painted arch. On the right,
            there is a bumpy design that falls to about mid-page. On the top left, there are two
            conifer-type flowers. Around the bottom-half of the page, there are similar swish-y
            designs with the bumpy design on the right. </description>
        <line n="1"/>The <nature type="plant">petals</nature> were voluminous enough to be stirred
            <line n="2"/>by the <nature type="sky">summer breeze</nature>, and when they moved, the
            <line n="3"/><color>red</color>, <color>blue</color> and <color>yellow</color> lights
        passed one over the <line n="4"/>other, staining an inch of the <color>brown</color>
        <nature type="ground">earth</nature> beneath with a <line n="5"/>spot of the most intricate
        colour. The light fell either <line n="6"/>upon the smooth, <color>grey</color> back of a
            <nature type="ground">pebble</nature>, or, the shell <line n="7"/>of a <nature
            type="animal">snail</nature> with its <color>brown</color>, <shape>circular</shape>
        veins, or falling into <line n="8"/>a <nature type="sky">raindrop</nature>, it expanded with
        such intensity of <color>red</color>, <color>blue</color>
        <line n="9"/>and <color>yellow</color> the thin walls of <nature type="sky">water</nature>
        that one expected <line n="10"/>them to burst and disappear. Instead, the <nature type="sky"
            >drop</nature> was <line n="11"/>left in a second <color>silver grey</color> once more,
        and the light now <line n="12"/>settled upon the flesh of a <nature type="plant"
            >leaf</nature>, revealing the branching thread of <line n="13"/>fibre beneath the
        surface, and again it <line n="14"/>moved on and spread its illumination in <line n="15"
        />the vast <color>green</color> spaces beneath the dome of <line n="16"/>the
            <shape>heart-shaped</shape> and <shape>tongue-shaped</shape>
        <nature type="plant">leaves</nature>. </page>

    <page n="6" facs="../docs/img/page6.jpg">
        <description resp="#edm"> An arch with broad swirls sits on the top margin. A line runs along
            the left and right margins. At the bottom, centered under the text, there are two
            flowers that seemingly come from the same origin. They sit upon large leaves that cast a
            thick shadow. </description>
        <line n="1"/>Then the <nature type="sky">breeze</nature> stirred rather more briskly
        overhead <line n="2"/>and the colour was flashed into the air above, into <line n="3"/>the
        eyes of the men and women who walk in <nature type="plant">Kew <line n="4"/>Gardens</nature>
        in July. <line n="5"/>The figures of these men and women straggled past the <line n="6"
            /><nature type="plant">flower-bed</nature> with a curiously irregular movement not <line
            n="7"/>unlike that of the <color>white</color> and <color>blue</color>
        <nature type="animal">butterflies</nature> who crossed <line n="8"/>the <nature
            type="ground">turf</nature> in zig-zag flights from bed to bed. The man <line n="9"/>was
        about six inches in front of the woman, strolling care- <line n="10"/>lessly, while she bore
        on with greater purpose, only turning <line n="11"/>her <nature type="human-body"
            >head</nature> now and then to see that the children were <line n="12"/>not too far
        behind. The man kept this distance in front <line n="13"/>of the woman purposely, though
        perhaps unconsciously, <line n="14"/>for he wished to go on with his thoughts. </page>

    <page n="7" facs="../docs/img/page7.jpg">
        <description resp="#edm"> Going from the top right, moving oounter-clockwise and ending at
            the bottom right, there is a bouncy swirly design that ends in a rose-shaped flower. </description>
        <line n="1"/>"Fifteen years ago I came here with <line n="2"/>Lily," he thought. "We sat
        somewhere over <line n="3"/>there by a <nature type="ground">lake</nature> and I begged her
        to marry me <line n="4"/>all through the hot afternoon. How the <nature type="animal"
            >dragon- <line n="5"/>fly</nature> kept circling round us: how clearly I see <line n="6"
        />the <nature type="animal">dragon-fly</nature> and her <tech type="cloth">shoe</tech> with the <shape>square</shape>
        <line n="7"/><color>silver</color>
        <tech type="cloth">buckle</tech> at the toe. All the time I spoke <line n="8"/>I saw her
        <tech type="cloth">shoe</tech> and when it moved impatiently <line n="9"/>I knew without looking up what she was going
            <line n="10"/>to say: the whole of her seemed to be in her <tech type="cloth"
            >shoe</tech>. <line n="11"/>And my love, my desire, were in the <nature type="animal"
            >dragon-fly</nature>; <line n="12"/>for some reason I thought that if it settled <line
            n="13"/>there, on that <nature type="plant">leaf</nature>, the broad one with the <line
            n="14"/><color>red</color>
        <nature type="plant">flower</nature> in the middle of it, if the <line n="15"/><nature
            type="animal">dragon-fly</nature> settled on the <nature type="plant">leaf</nature> she
        would <line n="16"/>say "Yes" at once. </page>


    <page n="8" facs="../docs/img/page8.jpg">
        <description resp="#edm"> Along the left margin, there is a tree, with a branch that cuts
            across the top margin. One third of the way down the page, there is another tree branch
            sprouting from the text. At the very bottom of the page are three thick black lines. </description>
        <line n="1"/>But the <nature type="animal">dragon-fly</nature> went round and round: it
            <line n="2"/>never settled anywhere—of course not, happily <line n="3"/>not, or I
        shouldn't be walking here with Eleanor <line n="4"/>and the children—Tell me, Eleanor. D'you
            <line n="5"/>ever think of the past?" <line n="6"/>"Why do you ask, Simon?" <line n="7"
        />"Because I've been thinking of the past. <line n="8"/>I've been thinking of Lily, the
        woman I might <line n="9"/>have married.... Well, why are you silent? Do <line n="10"/>you
        mind my thinking of the past?" <line n="11"/>"Why should I mind, Simon? Doesn't one always
            <line n="12"/>think of the past, in a <nature type="plant">garden</nature> with men and
            <line n="13"/>women lying under the <nature type="plant">trees</nature>? Aren't they
        one's <line n="14"/>past, all that remains of it, those men and women, <line n="15"/>those
        ghosts lying under the <nature type="plant">trees</nature>,... one's happiness, <line n="16"
        />one's reality?" <line n="17"/>"For me, a square <color>silver</color>
        <tech type="cloth">shoe buckle</tech> and a <line n="18"/><nature type="animal"
            >dragon-fly</nature>—" </page>

    <page n="9" facs="../docs/img/page9.jpg">
        <description resp="#edm"> The top of the page has simplistic rope-braid like patterns that
            somewhat connects to the side margin patterns. The side margin patterns are two loose
            swiggle lines. Around the bottom half of the page another squiggle line joins the three,
            then travels down and under the under margin patterns. The bottom area has big curly
            loops nesting black dots between it and the text. </description>
        <line n="1"/>"For me, a kiss. Imagine six little girls sitting <line n="2"/>before their
            <tech type="parts">easels</tech> twenty years ago, down by <line n="3"/>the side of a
            <nature type="ground">lake</nature>, painting the <nature type="plant"
            >water-lilies</nature>, <line n="4"/>the first <color>red</color>
        <nature type="plant">water-lilies</nature> I'd ever seen. And <line n="5"/>suddenly a kiss,
        there on the back of my <line n="6"/><nature type="human-body">neck</nature>. And my <nature
            type="human-body">hand</nature> shook all the after- <line n="7"/>noon so that I
        couldn't paint. I took out <line n="8"/>my <tech type="cloth">watch</tech> and marked the
        hour when I <line n="9"/>would allow myself to think of the kiss <line n="10"/>for five
        minutes only—it was so precious— <line n="11"/>the kiss of an old
            <color>grey</color>-<nature type="human-body">haired</nature> woman with <line n="12"/>a
            <nature type="human-body">wart</nature> on her <nature type="human-body">nose</nature>,
        the mother of all my <line n="13"/>kisses all my life. Come, Caroline, come, <line n="14"
        />Hubert. <line n="15"/>"They walked on past the <nature type="plant">flower-bed</nature>,
        now <line n="16"/>walking four abreast, and soon diminished in <line n="17"/>size among the
            <nature type="plant">trees</nature> and looked half <color>trans- <line n="18"
            />parent</color> as the <nature type="sky">sunlight</nature> and shade swam over their
            <line n="19"/>backs in large trembling irregular patches. </page>

    <page n="10" facs="../docs/img/page10.jpg">
        <description resp="#edm"> Wildly sprouting leaves come from the bottom of the page, and
            climbs up the margins. At the top, there are trumpet-flower-like designs. </description>
        <line n="1"/>In the <shape>oval</shape>
        <nature type="plant">flower bed</nature> the <nature type="animal">snail</nature>, whose
            shell<line n="2"/>had been stained <color>red</color>, <color>blue</color>, and
            <color>yellow</color> for the<line n="3"/>space of two minutes or so, now appeared
            to<line n="4"/>be moving very slightly in its shell, and next<line n="5"/>began to
        labour over the <nature type="ground">crumbs of loose<line n="6"/>earth</nature> which broke
        away and rolled down<line n="7"/>as it passed over them. It appeared to<line n="8"/>have a
        definite goal in front of it, differing <line n="9"/>in this respect from the singular high
        stepping <line n="10"/>angular green <nature type="animal">insect</nature> who attempted to
        cross <line n="11"/>in front of it, and waited for a second with<line n="12"/>its antennæ
        trembling as if in deliberation, <line n="13"/>and then stepped off as rapidly and
            strangely<line n="14"/>in the opposite direction.</page>
    <page n="11" facs="../docs/img/page11.jpg">
        <description resp="#edm"> Tall reed-like plants sprout from the bottom left corner, and end
            in curly lines that have straight shading lines above them to convey petals. The reed
            plants bend at the top margin and curve over the text. On the right side, there is
            another reed plant that simply climbs the right margin side and blooms at the top. </description>
        <line n="1"/><color>Brown</color>
        <nature type="ground">cliffs</nature> with deep <color>green</color>
        <nature type="ground">lake</nature>s <line n="2"/>in the hollows, flat, blade-like <nature
            type="plant">trees</nature><line n="3"/>that waved from <nature type="plant"
            >root</nature> to tip, round <nature type="ground">boulders</nature><line n="4"/>of
            <color>grey</color>
        <nature type="ground">stone</nature>, vast crumpled surfaces of a<line n="5"/>thin crackling
        texture—all these objects lay<line n="6"/>across the <nature type="animal">snail</nature>'s
        progress between one stalk<line n="7"/>and another to his goal. Before he had<line n="8"
        />decided whether to circumvent the arched<line n="9"/>tent of a <nature type="plant">dead
            leaf</nature> or to breast it there<line n="10"/>came past the bed the feet of other
            human<line n="11"/>beings.</page>
    <page n="12" facs="../docs/img/page12.jpg">
        <description resp="#edm">On the left and right margins there are 4 lines that go up and connect to a bumpy line that looks similar to a column. The bottom margin has one long bumpy line with large black cradled in the dips of the bumps. On the top margin, there are two arched lines in the center with two square-like shapes on the corners. </description>
        <line n="1"/>This time they were both men. The<line n="2"/>younger of the two wore an
            expression<line n="3"/>of perhaps unnatural calm; he raised his<line n="4"/><nature
            type="human-body">eyes</nature> and fixed them very steadily in front<line n="5"/>of him
        while his companion spoke, and<line n="6"/>directly his companion had done speaking<line
            n="7"/>he looked on the <nature type="ground">ground</nature> again and some-<line n="8"
        />times opened his <nature type="human-body">lips</nature> only after a long pause<line
            n="9"/>and sometimes did not open them at all.<line n="10"/>The elder man had a
        curiously uneven and<line n="11"/>shaky method of walking, jerking his hand<line n="12"
        />forward and throwing up his <nature type="human-body">head</nature> abruptly,<line n="13"
        />rather in the manner of an impatient carriage<line n="14"/><nature type="animal"
            >horse</nature> tired of waiting outside a <tech type="building">house</tech>; but<line
            n="15"/>in the man these gestures were irresolute and<line n="16"/>pointless. He talked
        almost incessantly; he<line n="17"/>smiled to himself and again began to talk,<line n="18"
        />as if the smile had been an answer. </page>
</xml>
